A Guide to the Patrick County [Virginia] Oral History Project Records, 1980-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Patrick County [Virginia] Oral History Project Records, 1980-1981
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Patrick County Project
Ms1983-007
30 Cubic Feet 30 boxes (Boxes 1-13, 17, 17a, 17b are in larger record Cartons 1 & 2), including 202 cassette tapes, 74 sound reel to reel tapes, 80 slides, and 1 16mm film reel.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Patrick County Oral History Project Records were donated to Special Collections in 1982.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of taped interviews; transcripts; biographical information about the interviewees; a subject card index to the interviews; a film, "Up and Down These Roads: a Rural County in Transition"; slide/tape programs; and such project documents as the original proposal, the final report, photographs, publicity clippings, and program posters. For a published guide to the collection, available in Special Collections, see Addison catalog record.
Historical Note
Sponsored by the Blue Ridge Regional Library and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University to explore the theme of "Continuity and Change in a Rural Community." It was conducted between September 1980 and August 1982. The project began by presenting a series of folklife programs on local traditions of music, dance, verbal art, history, and material culture; continued by collecting and transcribing taped oral histories of families and communities, building a collection of photographs of the county's past and present, and expanding the public branch library's and the University library's collections in regional literature, folk culture, and history; and then combining these activities as resources for producing a series of public programs which pursued the basic theme of "continuity and change" in this rural Southwest Virginia county.
Arrangement
This collection is in its original order, although some boxes have been condensed. Audio boxesoxes 1-12, which contain cassette tapes, are now in Boxes 1 and 2. Please note: Because materials were consolidated, there are no boxes 16, 21, or 26.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
There is also a published history and guide to the collection: Perry, Thomas David. 2009. Patrick County Oral History Project: A Guide. Ararat, Va: Laurel Hill Publishing. Spec Large F232 .P3 P4745 2009.
Separated Materials
Two copies of the film "Up and Down These Roads" were found in this collection were removed and cataloged for the Newman Library Film Collection.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Patrick County Project
Subjects:
Folklore -- Virginia -- Patrick County; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Patrick County (Va.) -- History; Patrick County (Va.). Social life and customs
Genre and Form Terms:
Oral histories (document genres)
Contents List
- Patrick County Project A/V Materials
  - Patrick County Project Cassette Tapes
    - Ayers, C. - Clark, J. Myron (Box 1 (in Carton 1))
    - Clark, J. – Culler, C. (Box 2 (in Carton 1))
    - East, G. – Hall, D. (Box 3 (in Carton 1))
    - Hopkins, B. – Houchins, M. (Box 5 (in Carton 1))
    - Howell, R. – Mayo Mountain Singers (Box 6 (in Carton 1))
    - Mitchell, I. – Pendleton, B. (Box 7 (in Carton 1))
    - Hall, P. – Hooker, J. (Box 4 (in Carton 2))
    - Penn, B. – Roberson, W. (Box 8 (in Carton 2))
    - Shelor, B. – Slate, S. (Box 9 (in Carton 2))
    - Spangler, C. – Terry, N. (Box 10 (in Carton 2))
    - Thomas, J – Weaver, N. (Box 11 (in Carton 2))
    - Williams, D. – Worley, L. (Box 12 (in Carton 2))
    - "Hard Times" slideshow and cassette tape (Box 29)
  - Patrick County Project Reel to Reel Tapes
    - Ayers, C. - Clifton, E. (Box 13)
    - Clifton, Fred - Harris, Oscar (Box 13a)
    - Hooker, J. - McAlexander, E. (Box 13b)
    - Martin, Callie - Roberson, W. (Box 14)
    - Shelor, Bertie - Thompson, M. (Box 14a)
    - Trinity Church of God - Worley, Lucy T. (Box 14b)
    - Fulcher, Alice #1 (Box 30)
    - Plaster, James (Box 30)
    - Weaver, Mr. and Mrs. Noel (Box 30)
    - Impact Series: "Growing Up in Patrick County" (Box 30)
    - Reel to reel tapes: "Community Life in Patrick County" and "Making a Living in Patrick County" (Box 18b)
  - Patrick County Project Photographs and Slides
    - Photographs of project interviewees and local events (Box 18b)
    - 4 cases of slides from the project and Patrick County events (Box 18b)
    - Interviewee Photographs(?) (Oversize 1)
- Patrick County Project Papers
  - Patrick County Project Informational sheets on interviewees and tape logs (102 folders) (Box 15)
  - Patrick County Project (PCP) Interview files, including excerpts and biographical files (Box 20)
    - Patrick County Project – General, 1982-1984
    - PCP Interview – Barbour, Jr., Andrew Lee
    - PCP Interview – Boaz, James Clayton
    - PCP Interview – Bolt, Ruth Jean
    - PCP Interview – Cartner, W. Curtis
    - PCP Interview – Clark, Lady Louise
    - PCP Interview – Clark, Martin Filmore
    - PCP Interview – Clark, Moir Ayers
    - PCP Interview – Clifton, Elder Bennie
    - PCP Interview – Clifton, Fred
    - PCP Interview – Cruise, Crystal
    - PCP Interview – Edwards, Maron Allen
    - PCP Interview – Fain, Curtis Robert
    - PCP Interview – Foddell, Marvin and Turner (brothers)
    - PCP Interview – Foddrell, Posey
    - PCP Interview – Fulcher, Alice West
    - PCP Interview – Fulcher, Mr. and Mrs. (Rush and Edith)
    - PCP Interview – Handy, John and Novella
    - PCP Interview – Harbour, Kenneth Green
    - PCP Interview – Harris, Lois
    - PCP Interview – Harris, Oscar Allen
    - PCP Interview – Helms, Abraham and Eula Florence
    - PCP Interview – Hopkins, Early and Beulah
    - PCP Interview – Hopkins, Rev. Luther Noel
    - PCP Interview – Hopkins, Walter Thomas Dudley
    - PCP Interview – Howell, Ruby Underwood
    - PCP Interview – Hylton, Annie Hines
    - PCP Interview – Layman, William Edgar, Jr.
    - PCP Interview – McKenzie, Chester Nolen
    - PCP Interview – Mitchell, Ida Beasley
    - PCP Interview – New Hope Church Quilters
    - PCP Interview – Patrick County High School Pep Club
    - PCP Interview – Penn, Burgie Bett Lawson
    - PCP Interview – Pilson, Alpha Ella Morrison
    - PCP Interview – Plaster, James Russell
    - PCP Interview – Porter, Pam
    - PCP Interview – Rakes, Orvilla Sue
    - PCP Interview – Roberson, Winifred C.
    - PCP Interview – Shelor, Bertie
    - PCP Interview – Shelor, Lesse and Clarice
    - PCP Interview – Slate, Robert Samuel
    - PCP Interview – Smith River Boys
    - PCP Interview – Spangler, C. L.
    - PCP Interview – Spanger, Dorn Odell
    - PCP Interview – Strock, Stella May Hodges
    - PCP Interview – Thompson, Murray
    - PCP Interview – Trinity Church of God
    - PCP Interview – Walker, Mary Horner
    - PCP Interview – Williams, Glen A.
    - PCP Interview – Worley, Lucy T.
    - PCP Interview – Wood, Addie
    - PCP Interview – Wood, George and Claudia
    - PCP Interview – Woodall, Ethel
    - PCP Interview – Williams, Lena Lampe
    - PCP Interview – Williams, Virgil Roosevelt and Lowell Ella
    - Patrick County Project Log and Interview List
    - Patrick County Project Interviewers
  - Patrick County Project Files
    - "Final Narrative Report Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," February 23, 1983 (Box 19)
    - "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," project proposal, February 19, 1980 (Box 19)
    - Research materials (Box 19)
    - Administration (Box 22)
    - Budget (Box 22)
    - Costs (Box 22)
    - Advisory Committee (Box 22)
    - Bibliography (Box 22)
    - Bibliography Orders (Box 22)
    - Complimentary Copy of Bibliography (Box 22)
    - Chairman Supplemental Grant (Box 22)
    - Film (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Correspondence (Box 22)
    - Evaluation (Box 22)
    - Financial Records (Box 22)
    - Impact Posters (Box 22)
    - Interim Narrative Report for Patrick County (Box 22)
    - General (Box 22)
    - Correspondence – Returned photographs (Box 23)
    - Correspondence – Summer Folklife Festival (Box 23)
    - Correspondence – Egerton (Box 23)
    - Adult Education Programs (Box 23)
    - Mountain Mercantile (Box 23)
    - Questionnaires – Resident (Box 23)
    - Posters (Box 23)
    - Evaluations (Box 23)
    - Projected Expenses File (Box 23)
    - Old Patrick and New (Box 23)
    - Eden Preservation and Society Public Program (Box 23)
    - Transcriber (Box 23)
    - Mountain Passages (Box 23)
    - Public Information – up to 10/15/1980 (Box 23)
    - Public Information – after 10/15/1980 (Box 23)
    - Media (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Library Ideas (Box 23)
    - Key Events in Patrick County History (Box 23)
    - NEH Quarterly Reports (Box 23)
    - Early Drafts – NEH (Free State of Patrick) (Box 23)
    - Early Drafts – NEH (with Ann add-ins) (Box 23)
    - Early Drafts – NEH (Britt notes) (Box 23)
    - Minutes (Box 23)
    - Early Drafts – NEH (Library background) (Box 23)
    - Early Drafts – NEH (Reviewer's comments) (Box 23)
    - Early Drafts – NEH (Guidelines) (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence – Speer (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence – Endorsement letter (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence – McCombs (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence – Fine (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence – Eastman (Box 23)
    - Correspondence – Local (Box 23)
    - Staff Correspondence – Official (Box 23)
    - NPR – Susan Reilly (Box 23)
    - NEH Correspondence (Box 23)
    - Educational Clearing House (Box 23)
    - Chairman's Grant (Box 23)
    - Certificate of Recognition (Box 23)
    - Harris, Bud (Box 23)
    - Revised Budget (Box 23)
    - Old Budgets – NEH (Box 23)
    - Correspondence – Advisory committee (Box 23)
    - Advisory Committee (Box 23)
    - Officials' Addresses (Box 23)
    - Local Addresses (Box 23)
    - Interviewers – Correspondence (Box 23)
    - Interviews – Who's interviewing whom (Box 23)
    - Interviewer Information Forms (Box 23)
    - Interview Subjects (Box 23)
    - Interviewers – Workshops (Box 23)
    - NEH Quarterly Reports (3 folders) (Box 24)
    - Recipes (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires – 11/3/1980 Program (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires – History Alive (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires – Summer Folklife Program (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires – Community Life (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires – Impact Series (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires – Making a Living (Box 24)
    - Questionnaires –Impact Series (Box 24)
    - Summer Folklife Series (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Summer Folklife Series – Final Report (Box 24)
    - Releases (Box 24)
    - NEH Final Report (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – October 2, 1980 (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Victorian Christmas (Box 24)
    - Public Offerings – 1980-1981 (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Winter-Spring 1980-1981 (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Evaluation (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Patrick County Fair (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – ETSU (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Miscellaneous (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Crafts (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Historical Society (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Appalshop (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – Appalachian Book and Record Shop (Box 24)
    - Public Programs – VLA (Box 24)
    - NEH Quarterly Reports (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - NEH Final Narrative Report (Box 24)
    - NEH Final Report (Box 24)
    - Film – Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Film Script (Box 24)
    - Film Distributors (Box 24)
    - Film Credit Debate (Box 24)
    - Film Brochure – A He (Box 24)
    - Filming – Meadows of Dan School Releases (Box 24)
    - Enterprise Indexing (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Scripts (Box 24)
    - Folklore – Films, Books (Box 24)
    - Folklore – Conferences (Box 24)
    - Folklore – Gooseberry Vine (VPI) (Box 24)
    - Film Evaluation – Stuart Courthouse (Box 24)
    - Film Evaluation – Meadows of Dan (Box 24)
    - Film Evaluation – Homestead (Box 24)
    - Film – Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Ideas for Future Programs (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Public Programs (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Programs (Box 24)
    - Film – Edgerton Brochure (Box 24)
    - Interview Subjects – Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Interviews – Fair (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Scripts (Box 24)
    - Impact Series –Conclusions, Correspondence (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Growing Up in Patrick County (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Hard Times (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Making a Living in Early Patrick (Box 24)
    - Impact Series – Community Life (Box 24)
    - Content Analysis (Box 24)
    - Interviewers – Notes (Box 24)
    - Tapes and Transcripts (Box 24)
    - Patrick County Project: Clippings (Box 25)
    - Public Information: Patrick County Project (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Releases (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Letterhead & Promotion Materials (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Public Program & Press Conference, October 2, 1980 (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Publicity Correspondence (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Pictures (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Press Kit, October 2, 1980 (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Memoranda (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Library Orders (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Library Materials (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Mailing List (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Materials (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Advisory Minutes (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Mountain Passages (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: NEH Reports (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Personnel (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Memorandum of Understanding (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Posters (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Printouts (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Public Programs, General (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Reference Materials (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: The Reynolds Homestead (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Summer 1980 (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Summer Folklife Series (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Staff Meeting Minutes (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Staff Meeting, February 13, 1981 (Box 25)
    - Patrick County Project: Staff Meeting, October 2, 1981 (Box 25)
    - Subject Index #1 (Box 17 (in Box 30))
    - Subject Index #2 (Box 17a (in Box 30))
    - Subject Index #2 (c.2) (Box 17b (in Box 30))
    - Patrick County, Continuity and Change in a Rural Community, NEH Grant Application (3 copies) (Box 30)
    - Background Files and Correspondence (Box 30)
    - Newspapers (Box 30)
    - Appalachia: Age-Old Struggles in a New Era posters (Oversize 1)
  - Patrick County Oral History Transcripts (bound)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, A-C (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, F-Ha (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, Ho-Hy (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, L-R (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, S (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, T-W (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, A-C, c.2 (Box 28)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, F-Ha, c.2 (Box 29)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, Ho-Hy, c.2 (Box 29)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, L-R, c.2 (Box 29)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, S, c.2 (Box 29)
    - Patrick County Project, "Patrick County: Continuity and Change in a Rural Community," Oral History Transcripts, T-W, c.2 (Box 29)
- Preservation of Libraries Papers
  - Citizens Committee for Public Libraries (Box 27)
  - National Citizens for Public Libraries (Box 27)
  - National Commission on Libraries and Information Sciences/White House Conference (Box 27, Box 30)